<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<L5RCM>
  <School clanid="scorpion" name="Yogo Wardmaster" id="scorpion_yogo_wardmaster_school">
    <Trait>intelligence</Trait>
    <Affinity>special</Affinity>
    <Deficiency>special</Deficiency>
    <Honor>1.5</Honor>
    <Tags>
      <Tag>shugenja</Tag>
      <Tag>scorpion_shugenja</Tag>
    </Tags>
    <Skills>
      <Skill rank="1" id="calligraphy" emphases="Cipher"/>
      <Skill id="etiquette" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="investigation" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="lore_theology" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="spellcraft" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="stealth" rank="1"/>
      <PlayerChoose rank="1">
        <Wildcard>high</Wildcard>
        <Wildcard>low</Wildcard>
      </PlayerChoose>
    </Skills>
    <Spells>
      <Spell id="commune"/>
      <Spell id="sense"/>
      <Spell id="summon"/>
      <PlayerChoose count="3" element="*any" tag="wards"/>
      <PlayerChoose count="3" element="!void"/>
    </Spells>
    <Techs>
      <Tech name="Way of the Wardmaster" rank="1" id="scorpion_way_of_the_wardmaster">
        <Description>
The Yogo are masters at creating wards for later use. When
you cast any spell with the Wards keyword, you may Raise
a number of times equal to the spell's Mastery Level to instead
place the spell into a paper ward. Once this is done, the
paper ward will hold the spell “latent” until you activate it
(as a Simple Action) by placing it on a target. Only you may
activate your wards. The ward sticks to the target and immediately
discharge the spell, whose duration is measured normally
from that moment. If an area-effect spell is discharged
onto a living target, it will only affect that target.
Placing a paper ward on an unwilling target requires an
unarmed melee attack using a roll of Spellcraft / Agility.
An active ward may be physically torn/destroyed, which
instantly ends any ongoing spell effects; this requires a
Simple Action.
You cannot recover the spell slot of a spell which has
been cast into a paper ward until after the ward is discharged.
If a ward is damaged or destroyed before it is
discharged, it loses all power and you may regain the
spell slot normally.
      </Description>
      </Tech>
    </Techs>
    <Requirements/>
  </School>
  <School clanid="scorpion" name="Shosuro Actors" id="scorpion_shosuro_actors_school">
    <Trait>awareness</Trait>
    <Honor>1.5</Honor>
    <Tags>
      <Tag>ninja</Tag>
      <Tag>scorpion_ninja</Tag>
    </Tags>
    <Skills>
      <Skill id="acting" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="etiquette" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="knives" rank="1"/>
      <Skill id="meditation" rank="1"/>
      <Skill rank="1" id="sincerity" emphases="Deceit"/>
	  <Skill id="stealth" rank="1"/>
      <PlayerChoose rank="1">
        <Wildcard>high</Wildcard>
        <Wildcard>low</Wildcard>
      </PlayerChoose>
    </Skills>
    <Spells/>
    <Techs>
      <Tech name="The First Face" rank="1" id="scorpion_the_first_face">
		<Description>
The Shosuro Actor begins his career by learning the basics
of deception and mimicry, and takes his first steps on
the path of infiltrating the Empire. You learn one persona.
Any time you spend a Void Point on an Acting or Sincerity
(Deceit) Skill roll, you a bonus of +3k1 instead of the
normal +1k1.	  
		</Description>
	  </Tech>
      <Tech name="The Subtle Sting" rank="2" id="scorpion_the_subtle_sting">
		  <Description>
Shosuro Actors are expected to serve their clan as both infiltrators and assassins. 
You gain a bonus of +2k0 to your attack rolls when wielding a Small weapon.		  
		  </Description>
	  </Tech>

      <Tech name="The Second Face" rank="3" id="scorpion_the_second_face">
		  <Description>
The Actor’s training has now advanced enough to make
him a far more flexible and capable infiltrator. You learn a
second persona. In addition, you may now spend two Void
Points (rather than just one) when enhancing a Skill roll
with any of your School Skills. This stacks with the effects
of your Rank One ability.		  
		  </Description>
	  </Tech>
	  
      <Tech name="The Vipers Kiss" rank="4" id="scorpion_the_vipers_kiss">
		  <Description>
The Shosuro Actor intensifies his martial training to enable
swift and deadly assassinations of his targets. You
may attack as a Simple Action instead of a Complex Action
when using a Small-sized weapon.		  
		  </Description>
	  </Tech>

      <Tech name="The Third Face" rank="5" id="scorpion_the_third_face">
		  <Description>
The Shosuro Actor is now a true master of deception, infiltration,
and murder. You gain a third persona. In addition,
if you attack a foe who is unaware or does not expect
danger from you, your Raises are not limited by your Void.		  
		  </Description>
	  </Tech>
	  
    </Techs>
    <Requirements/>
  </School>
</L5RCM>
