<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<L5RCM>
  <School clanid="crab" name="Hiruma Yojimbo" id="crab_hiruma_yojimbo">
    <Tags>
      <Tag>alternate</Tag>
      <Tag>bushi</Tag>
      <Tag>crab_bushi</Tag>
      <Tag>crab_alternate</Tag>
    </Tags>
    <Techs>
      <Tech name="The Crab's Shell" rank="3" id="hiruma_yojimbo_crabs_shell">
        <Description>Those Hiruma tasked with protecting the lives of important
Crab personages understand that the best and most
effective means of defending them is to destroy their enemies
as quickly as possible. After making a successful
melee attack, you may immediately perform the Guard Action
as a Free Action (if your charge is close enough for
you to Guard). If you do so, you may add the amount by
which your attack roll exceeded your opponent’s Armor
TN to the Armor TN of your charge until your next Turn.
        </Description>
      </Tech>
    </Techs>
    <Skills />
    <Spells />
    <Requirements>
      <RequirementOption text="Hiruma Bushi 3 or Hiruma Scout 3">
        <Requirement field="crab_hiruma_bushi_school" type="school" min="2"/>
        <Requirement field="crab_ob_hiruma_scout_school" type="school" min="2"/>
      </RequirementOption>
      <Requirement field="defense" type="skill" min="3">Defense: 3</Requirement>
    </Requirements>
  </School>

  <School clanid="crab" name="Yasuki Enforcer" id="crab_yasuki_enforcer">
    <Tags>
      <Tag>alternate</Tag>
      <Tag>bushi</Tag>
      <Tag>crab_bushi</Tag>
      <Tag>crab_alternate</Tag>
    </Tags>
    <Techs>
      <Tech name="Gentle Encouragement" rank="2" id="yasuki_enforcer_gentle_encouragement">
        <Description>The enforcers of the Yasuki family know how to threaten
in such a way that thoroughly cows any potential opponent.
You may make a Contested Roll against any individual,
using your Willpower / Intimidation against their
Willpower / Etiquette. If you are successful, you gain a
bonus of +1k0 on all attack rolls made against that individual
during the first Round of combat against them
during your next skirmish. Each successful Raise made on
this Contested Roll increases your bonus by an additional
+1k0. If this Technique is activated during a skirmish, the
initial Contested Roll is a Complex Action
        </Description>
      </Tech>
    </Techs>
    <Skills />
    <Spells />
    <Requirements>
      <RequirementOption text="Yasuki Courtier 2 or Hida Pragmatist 2">
        <Requirement field="crab_yasuki_courtier_school" type="school" min="1"/>
        <Requirement field="crab_ob_hida_pragmatist_school" type="school" min="1"/>
      </RequirementOption>
      <Requirement field="intimidation" type="skill" min="3">Intimidation: 3</Requirement>
    </Requirements>
  </School>

</L5RCM>