<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<L5RCM>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_crab_hiruma" name="Ancestor, Hiruma">
    <Rank id="1" value="11"/>
    <Description>The man who founded the Hiruma family was a pragmatic warrior who employed speed, precision, and stealth to defeat powerful foes. His guidance makes it easier to follow in his footsteps, granting you a +1k0 bonus to your Stealth, Kenjutsu, and Kyujutsu skill rolls. Demands: If Hiruma watches over you, you can never willingly betray the Crab Clan or he will abandon you. However, as a pragmatic warrior who eschews many of the niceties of Bushido he will also abandon you if your Honor Rank ever rises higher than 5.0.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_crab_kaiu" name="Ancestor, Kaiu">
    <Rank id="1" value="9"/>
    <Description>The legendary master craftsmen who forged the Crab Clan Ancestral Sword that slew Hatsu-Suru no Oni. Kaiu founded the most potent engineering school in the Empire and his descendants built the Great Carpenter Wall. Kaiu’s guidance grants you a +3k1 bonus (instead of +1k1) any time you spend a Void Point on a Craft or Engineering skill roll. In addition, once per game year you may call on Kaiu’s inspiration and roll an appropriate Craft skill at TN 50 to create a minor awakened nemuranai. The initial powers of this magical item are chosen by the GM, but should start out weak (e.g. +1k0 to skills or damage rolls, for example) until the spirits within the item grow stronger over time. Demands: Kaiu abhors mediocrity, laziness, and failure. You must never deliberately produce Craft/Engineering work that is less than your best. This obviously includes keeping low dice on a skill roll but will also have many subtler role-play applications; such situations should be adjudicated by the GM.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_crane_doji_hayaku" name="Ancestor, Doji Hayaku">
    <Rank id="1" value="7"/>
    <Description>Doji’s youngest son, the founder of the Daidoji family, was a skilled warrior who spent two years hunting for his lost sister Konishiko. He ultimately retrieved her sword (and her soul) from the Shadowlands, but in the process he lost his voice and his hair turned white. Hayaku’s guidance grants you a +1k1 bonus to Lore: Shadowlands rolls and a Free Raise on all attacks with Spears. Demands: You must honor Hayaku’s sacrifi ces by dyeing your hair white. You can never abandon, betray, or endanger a member of the Doji family (or your charge if you are a yojimbo)—if you do, Hayaku abandons you in fury.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_crane_asahina" name="Ancestor, Asahina">
    <Rank id="1" value="9"/>
    <Description>A powerful and talented Phoenix Clan Fire shugenja who forsook the ways of violence and married into the Crane Clan, Asahina became one of the Empire’s foremost advocates of peace. His family maintains his traditions to this day. Asahina’s spiritual guidance grants you a +1k0 bonus on Meditation rolls and a +1k1 bonus to Spell Casting Rolls when casting a non-damaging spell with the Craft or Defense keywords. Demands: Asahina expects you to live up to his ideals of absolute pacifi sm. If you ever willingly and deliberately harm a living creature, even a Tainted creature, he forsakes you.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_dragon_agasha_gc" name="Ancestor, Agasha">
    <Rank id="1" value="6"/>
    <Rank id="2" value="10"/>
    <Description>The founder of the Agasha family was an isolated researcher who studied the Elements and learned their secrets. Although much of her family joined the Phoenix, she remains loyal to the Dragon and appears only to those of her descendents found within that clan. Agasha’s insights into the true nature of the Elements grant you a +1k0 bonus to Spell Casting Rolls with non-Void spells and a +1k1 bonus to all Spellcraft Skill rolls. If you spend 10 points on Agasha as an Ancestor, you are one of her most favored descendents and learn the secret spell “Transmute.”  Demands: Agasha was a pacifi st, and if you ever serve in war she will abandon you. However, she was once kidnapped by goblins, so she will not abandon a descendent who wages war against the Shadowlands (only).</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_dragon_togashi_yamatsu" name="Ancestor, Togashi Yamatsu">
    <Rank id="1" value="7"/>
    <Description>The tattooed man who captured Iuchiban’s soul during the Bloodspeaker’s second rampage has no direct blood descendents, but his spirit sometimes appears to guide later tattooed men—you may only take Yamatsu as an Ancestor if you are a member of the Dragon tattooed orders. Yamatsu’s favor grants two Ranks of Magic Resistance that only apply against maho. In addition, his courageous spirit grants you a +2k2 bonus to any Willpower roll to resist being possessed or magically controlled. Demands: Yamatsu will abandon you if you ever gain Taint of 1.0 or higher, or if you ever willingly use maho or a Shadowlands power.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_lion_kitsu" name="Ancestor, Kitsu">
    <Rank id="1" value="6"/>
    <Description>The spirit once known as Soli Tendo, Kitsu took human form to found the Kitsu family and died in defense of the human clan he joined so reluctantly. A true-blooded descendent of Kitsu who gains his favor can detect the presence of spirits and spirit portals. (This is a Perception roll, normally TN 25, although the GM may raise it for obscure or well-hidden spirits or portals). In addition, Kitsu’s guidance grants you +1k1 to all Lore: Spirit Realms rolls. Demands: Kitsu abandons you if you ever willingly harm a non-corrupted member of the five ancient races (or one of their descendants), or if you ever willingly cooperate with a Tsuno.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_lion_matsu_hitomi" name="Ancestor, Matsu Hitomi">
    <Rank id="1" value="7"/>
    <Description>Hitomi was one of the greatest heroes of the Lion Clan, a woman of faultless honor and courage. If you are honored with her guidance, her unshakable faith in Bushido grants you a +1k1 bonus to all rolls to resist Temptation, Intimidation, and Fear effects. Demands: Hitomi abandons you if you ever knowingly betray your daimyo or the Lion Clan, or if your Honor ever drops below 5.0.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_mantis_moshi_azami" name="Ancestor, Moshi Azami">
    <Rank id="1" value="6"/>
    <Description>Moshi (formerly Isawa) Azami received the blessing of Lady Sun and shared her insight with her followers, leading the Centipede to become the most devout followers of the Sun Goddess anywhere in the Empire. Prior to the twelfth century Azami is solely an ancestor for the Centipede Clan. Her guidance bestows the favor of the Sun upon you—you suffer no ill effects from the Sun (e.g. dehydration, sunburn, etc) and gain Reduction of 5 against fire (normal or magical). Demands: Azami was a profoundly pious woman. She will leave you if you commit any act of impiety or blasphemy against the Fortunes or the Celestial Heavens (deliberately or accidentally).</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_mantis_osusuki_akomachi" name="Ancestor, Osusuki &amp; Akomachi">
    <Rank id="1" value="5"/>
    <Description>The two ancestors known as Osusuki and Akomachi were actually kitsune spirits who forged an alliance with the nascent Fox Clan. They took human form, one man and one woman, and married into the Kitsune family, bonding the two groups by blood forever. Their guidance will only be bestowed on members of the Kitsune family who can claim a direct blood connection. The attention of Osusuki and Akomachi allows you to speak with animals and animal shapeshifter spirits; furthermore, their wisdom allows you to always fi nd food and water in the wilderness. Demands: Ososuki and Akomachi remain deeply tied to the animal spirits who birthed them. They will abandon you if you ever voluntarily or knowingly kill an animal or an animal spirit (except for self-defense, which they forgive).</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_phoenix_isawa" name="Ancestor, Isawa">
    <Rank id="1" value="12"/>
    <Description>The man known as Isawa was unquestionably the greatest shugenja in Rokugan, perhaps in the world, at the time the Kami fell to earth. His power over the Elements was of such potency that Shiba, a son of the Heavens, bent knee and pledged to protect Isawa’s line for all time in order to gain his aid against Fu Leng. Those who are honored with Isawa’s guidance gain +1k1 on all Spellcraft (Spell Research) rolls and learn 1 additional spell each time they gain a Shugenja School Rank. Demands: Isawa was a proud man who believed his family’s magic superior to all others. He abandons you if you ever lose a magical or scholarly competition with someone who is not themselves of the Isawa family.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_phoenix_naka_kaeteru" name="Ancestor, Naka Kaeteru">
    <Rank id="1" value="10"/>
    <Description>The man called Kaeteru lived when the Empire was young. His thirst for knowledge led him to wander the Empire as a monk, learning all he could and passing it on to others who wished to learn as well. Although it was never his intention, he gathered many followers and students and became known as a great teacher. Eventually he was invited to the Phoenix lands so they might learn from him as well. Due to his incredible wisdom and experience, Kaeteru was named the fi rst Grandmaster of the Elements by the Phoenix, and awarded the spiritual title of Naka. The first Grandmaster of the Elements spent much of his life in simple contemplation of the Elements. If you are honored with his guidance, his enlightened insights allow you to use the Meditation skill (two hours, skill roll at TN 30) to regain 1 Spell Slot in each Ring. Demands: Kaeteru was detached from mortal concerns and will abandon any descendent who becomes too involved in worldly matters. This may be represented mechanically by your character acquiring more than 3 Skill Ranks in Courtier or any Merchant or Low skill. Role-play can and should impact this as well, and the GM should adjudicate whether a character with Kaeteru’s guidance is involving himself too deeply in worldly affairs such as politics or money.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_scorpion_yogo" name="Ancestor, Yogo">
    <Rank id="1" value="6"/>
    <Description>The former Phoenix, originally husband to Asako, who was cursed by Fu Leng to betray the one he loved. Yogo joined the Scorpion Clan and started a new family there, studying the techniques that became Yogo ward magic. Yogo’s guidance grants you a +1k1 bonus to the Spell Casting Roll when casting any Wards spell, but due to your blood connection to him you automatically gain Bad Fortune: Yogo Curse for no points. Demands: Yogo abandons you if you ever fall in love, since this means you will succumb to his curse.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_scorpion_soshi_saibankan" name="Ancestor, Soshi Saibankan">
    <Rank id="1" value="5"/>
    <Description>The founder of Rokugan’s modern law-enforcement system was a clever and eccentric man who was nonetheless dedicated to maintaining law and order in a fractious Empire. The guidance of this famous judge grants you a bonus of +3k1 (rather than the usual +1k1) whenever you spend a Void Point on a roll using the Perception Trait or the Lore: Law skill. Demands: Saibankan was a loyal Scorpion but also a man deeply dedicated to upholding law and order. If you ever knowingly break the law or allow another to break it in your presence, Saibankan will abandon you… unless you did so on the orders of your superiors within the Scorpion Clan.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_unicorn_otaku" name="Ancestor, Otaku">
    <Rank id="1" value="7"/>
    <Description>The founder of the Otaku (later Utaku) family and the first Unicorn Clan Thunder, Otaku was a woman who founded a family led by women. She will only offer her guidance on women descended from her line. Otaku’s wisdom bestows an empathic connection to horses, granting you a +1k1 bonus to all Horsemanship skill rolls. Otaku’s ferocity and determination grant you a +1k0 bonus to attack rolls against male opponents Demands: Otaku will abandon you if you are ever deliberately cruel to a horse or if you ever challenge a man (whether to a duel or a competition) and then lose.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_unicorn_iuchi" name="Ancestor, Iuchi">
    <Rank id="1" value="8"/>
    <Description>Iuchi studied and mastered the ways of foreign magic, enabling the Unicorn to survive in the hostile world beyond the Burning Sands. His insights gave rise to the unique Unicorn style of magic known as meishodo. The guidance of Iuchi is bestowed on shugenja of his bloodline, and allows them to approach Rokugani spells in unconventional ways. While his spirit remains with you, you do not have a Deficient Element. Demands: So long as you wish to retain Iuchi’s favor, you may never pass up a chance to learn more about magic, even dangerous or blasphemous magic. Just because you know about it doesn’t mean you’ll use it, after all…</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_spider_chuda_bikimi" name="Ancestor, Chuda Bikimi">
    <Rank id="1" value="3"/>
    <Description>Chuda Bikimi was a corrupt, ruthless, and utterly evil maho-tsukai, a terrible phantom who moved throughout the Empire like a blade of darkness. He snatched victims from their beds, from their dojo, from all imaginable locations, never once seen by any save his victims. All those who were kidnapped met terrible fates in necromantic maho rituals. Even beyond death, Bikimi’s legacy persists and he bestows his sinister blessings on those engaged in similar evil schemes. His guidance grants you a +1k0 bonus to any Stealth Skill Roll. If you are a shugenja who practices maho, you may instead expend a spell slot to gain a +1k1 bonus to a Stealth Skill Roll. Demands: Bikimi has no respect for those who are foolish enough to expose themselves. If you ever willingly reveal yourself to an enemy, Bikimi will abandon you forever, with no chance to regain his favor.</Description>
  </Merit>
  <Merit type="spiritual" id="ancestor_spider_yogo_junzo" name="Ancestor, Yogo Junzo">
    <Rank id="1" value="6"/>
    <Description>Once a lord of the Scorpion, Yogo Junzo’s fury at the dissolution
of his clan following the Scorpion Clan Coup led him to betray his duty and open the Black Scrolls containing Fu Leng’s essence. He became a self-willed undead monstrosity and led a Shadowlands army into Rokugan, assailing temples and monasteries and putting dozens of great libraries to the torch. The effects of his campaign of destruction still haunt the Empire generations later. His dark blessings allow you to call on the most dire and blasphemous knowledge to enhance your power. For each Forbidden Knowledge Advantage you possess, you gain a bonus of +2 to the total of all Spellcasting Rolls, +4 if the roll is for casting a maho spell. You gain the same bonus for every Rank of Taint you possess. Demands: Junzo demands you follow him down the path of dark knowledge and ever-greater power. If you are ever presented with an opportunity to learn new forbidden knowledge (or to gain a new instance of the Forbidden Knowledge Advantage) and do not take it, even to preserve your reputation or secrecy, Junzo abandons you.</Description>
  </Merit>
</L5RCM>
